<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on John S Butler</title>
    <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on John S Butler</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Centre for Eye Research Ireland</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/ceri/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/ceri/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Neuroscience</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/comp-neuro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/comp-neuro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an ongoing, possibly Sisyphus, project in which I am writing iPython notebooks of mathematical models in Neuroscience. These notebooks are interactive webpages to illustrate and hopefully demystify the different mathematical models and also might be an aid to someone learning Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years I have worked with undergradute final year maths students to program up some of my favorite papers such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Izekivich model to simulate neuronal behaviour (Izekivich 2005);&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Neural Mass Model (also known as Dynamic Causal Modelling) to simulate EEG;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Models of decision making Notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sensory and Multisensory Development</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/multisensorydevelopment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/multisensorydevelopment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
My research investigates the developmental of unisensory and multisensory processing in typically developing children and children with developmental disorders such as Autism.
This research is being carried out in collaboration with Prof J. Foxe (Rochester University) and Prof Sophie Molholm (Albert Einstein College of Medicine).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Sensory Processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a recent paper I investigate the theory that children with Autism have an unreliabile neuronal response to sensory stimuli. Out results would suggest that sensory processing is equally reliable for children with Autism and neuro-typical controls.
Hence if the Neural Unreliability Thesis much more nuanced and needs further development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tpN0YN8DyTQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;autoplay; encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Selected References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;	&lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, S. Molholm, G. Andrade, J. J. Foxe, (2017) &#34;An Examination of the Neural Unreliability Thesis of Autism.&#34; Cerebral Cortex &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;	G. Andrade, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, G. Peters, S. Molholm, J. J. Foxe, (2016) &#34;Atypical visual and somatosensory adaptation in schizophrenia-spectrum disorders.&#34; &lt;em&gt;Translational Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    T. S. Altschuler, S. Molholm, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, M. R. Mercier, A. B. Brandwein, J. J. Foxe, (2013) &#34;The effort to close the gap: Tracking
    the development of illusory contour from childhood to adulthood with high-density electrical mapping&#34; &lt;em&gt;Neuroimage, 90&lt;/em&gt;, 360-373
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Audio Visual Integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have been involved in a series of studies investigating sensory (audio and visual) processing and multisensory (audio-visual) processing in children with Autism and Children with Niemann-Pick Type C.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QLMNLejBlDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;autoplay; encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h4&gt; Selected References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    G. Andrade, S. Molholm, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, S. Walkley, J. J. Foxe, (2014) &#34;Atypical multisensory integration in Niemann-Pick Type C disease
    - towards potential biomarkers&#34; &lt;em&gt;Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;, 9&lt;/em&gt;, 149
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Brandwein, J. J. Foxe, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, J. C. Bates, L. Shulman, H.P. Frey, S. Molholm, (2014) &#34;Neurophysiological indices of atypical
    auditory processing and multisensory integration are associated with symptom severity in autism spectrum disorder.&#34; Journal of Autism and Developmental
    Disorders
    &lt;br/&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;
Featured in international popular press such as        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.popsci.com/article/science/measuring-brainwaves-could-lead-objective-autism-diagnosis&#34;&gt;Time Magazine&lt;/a&gt;,
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/news/to-your-health/wp/2014/09/22/a-brain-wave-test-could-diagnose-autistic-kids-more-accurately-and-earlier/&#34;&gt;
            Washington Post
        &lt;/a&gt;
        and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cbsnews.com/news/brainwave-test-may-help-diagnose-autism/&#34;&gt;CBS news&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Brandwein, J. J. Foxe, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, N. Russo, H. Gomes, T. Altschuler, S. Molholm, (2012) &#34;Multisensory
    processing in children with Autism: High-density electrical mapping of audio-visual integration.&#34; Cerebral Cortex
    &lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;h3&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;
	  &lt;ul&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;John Foxe (University of Rochester/Albert Einstein College of Medicine)&lt;/li&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Sophie Molholm (Albert Einstein College of Medicine)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dystonia</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/dystonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/dystonia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt; Dystonia&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dystonia is one of the most common movement disorders with a prevelance in the population of 1 in every 1000 suffer from Dystonia. There is no single test that can be used to diagnose either of these disorders but they are recognised as a collection of symptoms.  Furthermore, there are no known cures just treatments to manage the symptoms hence there is a high impact on the quality of life and financial costs to managing the diseases. This cost is further exasperated by the growing aging population.
My research uses a variety of different techniques such as virtual reality, simple behavioural tasks and neuroimaging to gain insight on the disorders.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been involved in a series of studies looking at temporal discrimation as a behavioural endophenotype for Dystonia and a gateway to understanding the underlying mechanisms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe allowTransparency=&#34;true&#34; allowfullscreen height=&#34;415&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwheight=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://www.jove.com/embed/player?id=56310&amp;access=gz9r94te&amp;t=1&amp;s=1&#34; width=&#34;460&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Measurement &amp; Analysis of the Temporal Discrimination Threshold Applied to Cervical Dystonia&#34; href=&#34;https://www.jove.com/video/56310/measurement-analysis-temporal-discrimination-threshold-applied-to&#34;&gt;Measurement &amp; Analysis of the Temporal Discrimination Threshold Applied to Cervical Dystonia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Selected References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;		L. Williams, E. McGovern, O. Kimmich, A.Molloy, I. Beisser, J. S. Butler, F. Molloy, P.Logan, DG Healy, T Lynch, R Walsh, L Cassidy, P Moriarty, H Moore, T McSwiney, C Walsh,
S. O&#39;Riordan, M. Hutchinson, (2016) &#34;Epidemiological, clinical and genetic aspects of adult onset isolated focal dystonia in Ireland&#34;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;	B. Quinlivan, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, I Beiser, L Williams, E McGovern, S. O&#39;Riordan, M. Hutchinson,  R.B Reilly, (2016) &#34;Application of virtual reality head mounted display for investigation of human kinematics; a novel representation of the Posner cueing effect&#34; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neural Engineering&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;J S Butler*&lt;/strong&gt;, I Beiser, L Williams, E McGovern, F Molloy, T Lynch, D G Healy, H Moore, R Walsh, R B Reilly, S O&#39;Riordan, C Walsh, M Hutchinson (2015), &#34;Age-Related Sexual Dimorphism in Temporal Discrimination and in Adult-Onset Dystonia Suggests GABAergic Mechanisms.&#34;, &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Neurology&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    L. Williams, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler*&lt;/strong&gt;, A.Molloy&lt;sup&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;O. Kimmich, I. Beisser, E. McGovern, B. Quinlivan, S. O&#39;Riordan, R.B Reilly, M.
    Hutchinson, (Accepted) &#34;Women do it better: sexual dimorphism in temporal discrimination&#34; &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Neurology Feb 2015&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
    J. S. Butler, A.Molloy, L. Williams,&lt;sup&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;O. Kimmich, I. Beisser, E. McGovern, B. Quinlivan, S. O&#39;Riordan, M. Hutchinson, R.B Reilly, (2015) &#34;
    Non-parametric bootstrapping method for measuring the temporal discrimination threshold for Movement Disorders&#34; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neural Engineering&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A.Molloy, O. Kimmich, L. Williams,&lt;sup&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;J. S. Butler, I. Beisser, E. McGovern, R.B Reilly, S. O&#39;Riordan, C. Walsh, M. Hutchinson, (2015) &#34;Sun
    exposure is an environmental factor for the development of blepharospasm&#34; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery, and Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;br&gt; Featured in the Irish Medical Times and in &lt;a href=&#34;http://medicalxpress.com/news/2015-06-sunlight-exposure-latitude-linked-dystonia.html&#34;&gt;Medical Xpress&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;h3&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;
	  &lt;ul&gt;
	   &lt;li&gt;Prof Richard Reilly (Trinity College Dublin)&lt;/li&gt;
	   &lt;li&gt;Prof Michael Hutchinson (St Vincent&#39;s Hospital)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maths in the Wild</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/maths_in_the_wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/maths_in_the_wild/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://john-s-butler-dit.github.io/Maths-in-the-Wild/&#34;&gt;Maths in the Wild&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a series of workshops for primary and secondary school students. Through hands-on experiments 
and calculations, participants discover how maths and science—especially neuroscience—help us explore and understand the world around us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The workshops were developed by &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Nicole Beisiegel&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;myself, Dr. John Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, both of us teaching 
mathematics at Technological University Dublin. I combine my background in maths and neuroscience to design interactive experiments and 
analysis techniques that help us explore the world, while Nicole brings together maths and ocean science to investigate the natural environment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Originally created for the &lt;em&gt;TU Dublin Access and Outreach programme&lt;/em&gt;, these workshops continue to spark curiosity and 
show how mathematics connects to real-life experiences. All the details are on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://john-s-butler-dit.github.io/Maths-in-the-Wild/&#34;&gt;Maths in the Wild&lt;/a&gt; website.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile Brain Imaging (MoBI)</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/mobilebrainimaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/mobilebrainimaging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt;Neural Correlates of Self-Motion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have extended my work on self-motion perception to include Electroencephalography(EEG) to investigate the neural process involved in dual-tasking such as walking and performing a task and cortical processing of vestibular signals.
This new research area is known as mobile brain imaging (MoBI).
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/w-Zcb9h9M40&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;autoplay; encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Selected References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;	B. Malcolm, J. J. Foxe, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, Wenzhu B. Mowrey, S. Molholom, P. De Sanctis, (2017) &#34;Long-term test-retest reliability of event-related potential (ERP) recordings during treadmill walking using the mobile brain/body imaging (MoBI) approach&#34; Brain Research
&lt;p&gt;
    B. Malcolm, J. J. Foxe, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, P. De Sanctis, (2015) &#34;The aging brain shows less flexible reallocation of processing during
    dual-task walking: A Mobile Brain-Body Imaging (MOBI) Study&#34; &lt;em&gt;Neuroimage &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
     P. De Sanctis,&lt;strong&gt; J. S. Butler&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, F. Green, A. C. Snyder, J. J. Foxe, (2012) &#34;Mobile Brain/Body Imaging (MoBI): High-denisty
    electrical mapping of inhibitory processes during walking.&#34; IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society, San Diego.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    H. Nolan,&lt;strong&gt; J. S. Butler&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, R. Whelan, J. J. Foxe, H. H. B&amp;uuml;lthoff, R B. Reilly, (2012) &#34;Detecting Changes in Self-motion
    Heading: A High Density Electrophysiological Measure of Vestibular Processing.&#34; Experimental Brain Research, 219(1):1-11
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 H. Nolan R. Whelan R. Reilly, H. H. B&amp;uuml;lthoff, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, (2009) &#34;    &lt;em&gt;Acquisition of Human EEG Data during Linear Self-Motion on a Stewart Platform&lt;/em&gt;&#34;, IEEE Neural Engineering; 585-588.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;
	  &lt;ul&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Heinrich Bulthoff (Max Planck Institute)&lt;/li&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Jennifer Campos (Toronto Rehabilitation)&lt;/li&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Pierfilippo DeSanctis (Albert Einstein College of Medicine)&lt;/li&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;John Foxe (University of Rochester/Albert Einstein College of Medicine)&lt;/li&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Richard Reilly (Trinity College Dublin)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parkinson&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/parkinsonsdisease/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/parkinsonsdisease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;  Parkinson&#39;s Disease&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Approximately 1 in every 100 people over the age of 60 has Parkinson&#39;s disease. There is no single test that can be used to diagnose either of these disorders but they are recognised as a collection of symptoms.  Furthermore, there are no known cures just treatments to manage the symptoms hence there is a high impact on the quality of life and financial costs to managing the diseases. This cost is further exasperated by the growing aging population.
My research uses a variety of different techniques such as virtual reality, simple behavioural tasks and neuroimaging to gain insight on the disorders.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have been involved in research investigating sensory, motor and decision making processing in people with Parkinson&#39;s Disease with and without Freezing of Gait.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/D5rrpNGn-nw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;autoplay; encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Selected References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, C. Fearon, I. Killane, S M. Waechter, R.B Reilly, T.L. Lynch, (2017)
&#34;Motor Preparation Rather Than Decision-Making Differentiates Parkinson&#39;s Disease Patients With And Without Freezing of Gait&#34;
Clinical Neurophysiology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
C. Fearon, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler*&lt;/strong&gt;, L. Newman,  T.L. Lynch, R.B Reilly, (2015) &#34;Auditory, visual, and multisensory processing in Parkinson&#39;s disease&#34;  &lt;em&gt;Parkinsonism &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Collaborators&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Prof Richard Reilly (Trinity College Dublin)&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
   &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Prof Timothy Lynch (Mater Hospitcal)&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visual-Vestibular integration for self-motion processing</title>
      <link>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/visualvestibular/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://johnsbutler.netlify.app/project/visualvestibular/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1&gt; Visual Vestibular Integration&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I investigate the role of visual and vestibular inputs in self-motion (e.g. walking and driving) which I model using a Bayesian framework to make predictions of
how the sensory cues combine. This work required the use of state of the art motion simulators and virtual reality tools. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ThkymYRP1g8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;autoplay; encrypted-media&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h3&gt; Selected References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, J. L. Campos, H. H. B&amp;uuml;lthoff, (2014) &#34;The robust nature of visual-vestibular combination for heading.&#34; Experimental
    Brain Research
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    J. L. Campos, &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, H. H. B&amp;uuml;lthoff, (2014) &#34;Visual, and proprioceptive cue-weighting in travelled distance perception.&#34;
    Experimental Brain Research
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;J. S. Butler&lt;/strong&gt;, S. Smith, J. L. Campos, H. H. B&amp;uuml;lthoff. (2010) &#34;Bayesian integration of visual and vestibular information.&#34; Journal of
    Vision, Sep 1;10(11):23
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;
	  &lt;ul&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Heinrich Bulthoff (Max Planck Institute)&lt;/li&gt;
	  &lt;li&gt;Jennifer Campos (Toronto Rehabilitation)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
